A Guide to the Notebooks and Papers of Robert Gartrell, American Rhododendron Society,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Notebooks and Papers of Robert Gartrell, American Rhododendron Society
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10553-aw
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift from Donald H. Voss, 2003 January 9.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert Derby Gartrell was born in Atlanta, Georgia, in 1895 and trained as a chemist at Georgia Tech University. He married Nancy Reynolds, also of Georgia, and they had two daughters Jeanne Gartrell and Elizabeth Anne Gartrell, who married Donald H. Voss in 1952. He began his career with a Montreal testing laboratory during World War I, but in the 1920's he worked in Canada as a chemist for the Dominion Rubber Company eventually becoming director of development. Gartrell transferred to the Mechanical Goods Division of the U.S. Rubber Company in Passaic, New Jersey in 1931, becoming the entire division's manager of development, 1949-1958.
Beginning in the thirties, Gartrell decided to try to breed evergreen azaleas that would be hardy enough to thrive in northern New Jersey and have flowers similar to the hybrids from southern India. In 1937, the Gartrells moved to a large house on property they called "Robin Hill" where he began his breeding program with a large number of evergreen azaleas from the Tingle Nursery Company, Pittsville, Maryland.
According to Donald Voss, "By 1958 he had selected for further trial about 1,800 plants." This large number of plants presented a problem when he moved to a smaller place at Birchwood Drive, Wyckoff, New Jersey, in preparation for his retirement, and Lehman Tingle offered a field at his nursery for some of the plants (3 notebooks record these observations). By 1959, Gartrell was planting beds at Wyckoff and built a greenhouse there in 1960. There are notebooks recording his observations for all of these. In 1981, the Gartrells moved from Wyckoff, New Jersey, to a retirement home in Black Mountain, North Carolina.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the horticultural notes, observations, correspondence, and research materials, ca. 1950-2004, ca. 1,000 items (8 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3.5 linear feet) of Robert Derby Gartrell (1895-?), creator of the Robin Hill Evergreen Azalea Hybrids, which have become one of the most popular and widespread of the modern azaleas. Material types include notebooks, note cards, correspondence, citation, articles, talks, photographs, legal papers concerning the Robin Hill azaleas, and registration sheets.
Arrangement
The papers are organized in two series: Series I: Azalea Notebooks or Bed Books which are listed in two distinct groups by Robert Gartrell's son-in-law, Donald H. Voss (Boxes 1-5) and Series II: Correspondence and Topical Files (Boxes 6-8). he azalea notebooks were kept in the order listed by Voss in his notes to preserve easy access to the extra information in his notes. The second series of files are arranged chronologically within the folder and have combined some of the original folders to conserve space. They were not necessarily kept in the order indicated in Voss' notes.
Contents List
- Series I: Azalea Notebooks or Planting "Bed Books,"
  Numbers in Brackets indicate the numbers used by Donald H. Voss to describe the contents of the notebooks in his descriptions that accompanied the collection. Numbers with the parenthesis indicate the folder number within the box. For more complete information about these books, see the notes of Donald H. Voss in Box 7.
  - Subseries A: First Group
    - "Bed Books"- [1] Parent plants used in breeding program, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - "Bed Books"- [2] Bed F, third from side wall and [3] Bed J, planted May 30, 1958, 1952-1953, 1958 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - "Bed Books"- [4] Bed G 1953-1958 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - "Bed Books"- [5] Bed H, 1951-1958 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - "Bed Books"- [6] Bed A 1952, 1955 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - "Bed Books"- [7] Bed B, 1952, 1955 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - "Bed Books"- [8] Bed C, 1958 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - "Bed Books"- [9] Bed D, 1955 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - "Bed Books"- [10] Bed E and [11] Bed E-2, 1952-1959 (Box-folder 1:9)
    - "Bed Books"- [12] Main Park, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - "Bed Books"- [13]-[14] Behind Barn, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - "Bed Books"- [15] Bed J at Birchwood Drive, Wyckoff, New Jersey, 1959 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - "Bed Books"- [16] Bed K at Birchwood Drive, Wyckoff, New Jersey, 1959 (Box-folder 1:13)
    - "Bed Books"- [18] Bed M, 1960 (Box-folder 1:14)
    - "Bed Books"- [19]-[20] Bed N, 1960, 1963 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - "Bed Books"- [21] Bed JJ, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - "Bed Books"- [22] Bed O, 1961 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - "Bed Books"- [23] Bed P, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - "Bed Books"- [24] Bed R, 1961 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - "Bed Books"- [25] Bed S, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - "Bed Books"- [26] Bed LL, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - "Bed Books"- [27] Bed T 1964-1965 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - "Bed Books"- [28] Tingle Nursery, Pittsville, Maryland, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2:9)
    - "Bed Books"- [29] Tingle Nursery, Pittsville, Maryland, 1962 (Box-folder 2:10)
    - "Bed Books"-[30] Tingle Nursery, Pittsville, Maryland, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Subseries B: Second Group
    - "Bed Books"- [1] Bed N and [2] Bed O, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - "Bed Books"- [3] Bed P, 1961 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - "Bed Books"- [4] Bed T, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - "Bed Books"- [5] Bed T-2, 1969 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - "Bed Books"- [6] Bed W, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - "Bed Books"- [7] Bed X and [8] Bed W, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - "Bed Books"- [9] Bed D and [10] Bed S, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 3:7)
    - "Bed Books"- [11] Bed X, 1965-1970 (Box-folder 4:1)
    - "Bed Books"- [12] Bed S Revised, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 4:2)
    - "Bed Books"- [13] Bed N and [14] Bed O, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 4:3)
    - "Bed Books"- [15] Bed Z, 1967 (Box-folder 4:4)
    - "Bed Books"- [16] Bed U and [17] Bed V, 1968 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - "Bed Books"- [18] Bed X, 1968 (Box-folder 4:6)
    - "Bed Books"- [19] Bed Z, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 4:7)
    - "Bed Books"- [20] Bed B, [21] Bed C, and [22] Bed F, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 5:1)
    - "Bed Books"- [23] Bed E and [24] Bed G, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5:2)
    - "Bed Books"- [25] Bed W, [26] Bed Z, and [27] Bed Z, New Section, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 5:3)
    - "Bed Books"- [28] Bed A, [29] Bed AA, and [33] Bed AAA, 1972 (Box-folder 5:4)
    - "Bed Books"- [31] Bed A, [32] Bed AA, and [33] Bed AAA, 1972 (Box-folder 5:5)
    - "Bed Books"- [34] Bed HH and [35] Bed HA, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 5:6)
    - "Bed Books"- [36] Bed M, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 5:7)
- Series II: Correspondence and Topical Files
  - American Rhododendron Society Bronze Medal Citation Awarded to Robert D. Gartrell by the New York Chapter, 1975 June 6 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Article- The Flowering Forest of Joe Gable,1954 March 20 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Azalea Notes- Beltville, Maryland Agricultural Research Service Pamphlets and Articles (Chiefly Printed), but also including correspondence about fertilizer, artificial light and azalea growth rates (September 5, 1963), 1961-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Azaleas- Old Records, includes a letter from Henry T. Skinner concerning Gartrell's names for his azaleas (January 3, 1966), 1952-1968 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Azalea Photographs, 8x10 Photographs by [Emil] Hager, 1974, 1978, n.d. (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Azalea Planting Charts, ca. 1970-1980 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Cards (5x8) listing recipients of Plant Material from Robert Gartrell, ca. 1971-1982 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Correspondence A-L, includes Gay Arsen; Ronald Bare; Hugh A. Caldwell; Arthur W. Frazer; Fred C. Galle, Callaway Gardens; Ray Goldsby; Richard H. Hugger; Ellis Jones; Masaki Kunishige, Japan; Tom Laavy; and David Goheen Leach, 1965-1981 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Correspondence M-Z, includes Jane McKay; John Mackenroth; Ronnie Palmer; Ralph Pennington; Dr. Max L. Resnick; Arnold J. Teese, Australia; and Jef Van Meulder, Belgium, 1974-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Correspondence- Pat and Robert Erb and George S. Lee, Jr. both of New Canaan, Connecticut, containing the Erb's list of their Robin Hill Azaleas ( 1979) and George Lee's list of his Robin Hill Azaleas (1974); Also present are two booklets, Catalogue of Plants Olive W. Lee Memorial Garden and Gable Azaleas in the Olive W. Lee Memorial Garden,1973-1979, n.d. (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Correspondence- Gardens and Nurseries, includes: Azalea Acres Farm, Maryland, Frank B. White, Jr.; Holly Heath Nursery, Wading River, New York, Matt Nosel, Nurseryman; Holly Hills, Inc., Henry R. Schroeder & Sons; Hydon Nurseries Ltd; and Longwood Gardens, 1973-1981 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Correspondence- Gardens and Nurseries, includes: Midland Park Lumber & Supply Company; Miscellaneous Nurseries and Products; Miles Nursery, Jesse and Cecelia Miles; Planting Fields Arboretum; Pless Nursery; Skylands Botanical Gardens; Tingle Nurseries; The Wayside Gardens Company; and Weston Nursery, 1931, 1960-1980, n.d. (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Correspondence- Betty Hager, 1972-1982 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Correspondence- George W. Harding, 1972-1982 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Correspondence- Allen and Irene Harris, New Zealand, 1973-1978 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Correspondence- Mrs. Julian W. Hill ("Polly") 1972-1980 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Correspondence- Betty Layman, 1974-1979, n.d. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Correspondence- Franklin H. West, M.D., 1971-1978 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Correspondence- Thomas and Gladys Wheeldon, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Evaluation of Gartrell Hybrids in Notebook, ca. 1972-1978 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Evaluation of Gartrell Hybrids- Looseleaf, ca. 1963-1974 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Evergreen Azalea Committee of the American Rhododendron Society, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Gartrell's Robin Hill Azaleas- Observations and Evaluations by George W. Harding, including correspondence of Harding with Gartrell, 1971-1982, n.d. (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Glenn Dale, Maryland Plant Introduction Station, 1950-1973 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Note cards of Observations concerning the Plants at Wyckoff, New Jersey, ca. 1981 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - Notes by Donald H. Voss concerning this collection, especially the Planting Bed Books,ca. 2003 (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Plant Pests, Growth, and Techniques- Brochures, etc., 1958-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas, 1972-1981 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas- Correspondence, 1978-1982, 1999 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas- Descriptions, 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas- Descriptions, Both Selections- Stud Book (formerly in a black three-ring notebook) and Data from the Azalea Studbooks of Robert D. Gartrell by Donald H. Voss, ca. 1973, [ca. 1995] (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas Nursery- Legal Papers, 1964, 1974-1981 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas Registration- Correspondence, chiefly Ed Parker, Robert D. Gartrell, Donald H. Voss, and Dr. Alan C. Leslie, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas Registration- Correspondence, n.d. (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas Registration Sheets, n.d., 1 of 2 folders. (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Robin Hill Azaleas Registration Sheets, n.d., 2 of 2 folders. (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Robin Hill Hybrid Azaleas by W. Ronald Waldron, U.S. National Arboretum, with correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Talks and Articles about Azaleas by Robert D. Gartrell, 1969-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 8:12)